<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Academic</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 21:44:27 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Academic</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protein Aggregation Dynamics in Alzheimer&#39;s Disease</title>
      <link>/project/protein-aggregation-dynamics-in-alzheimers-disease/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 21:44:27 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/protein-aggregation-dynamics-in-alzheimers-disease/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is a complex neurodegenerative disorder, clinically characterized by a gradual decline in memory and impairment of other cognitive functions like communication, movement, higher visual processing, and language inability. Polymorphism among amyloid-β (Aβ) aggregates are emerging as the main contributors to the observed phenotypic diversity in sporadic Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease (sAD). Aggregation of Aβ is susceptible to several heterotypic factors, and lipids (LDs) are the most important physiological agents to interact with and modulate Aβ aggregation. Therefore, understanding the mechanism of how LDs modulate Aβ aggregation to generate polymorphic strains along competing pathways is crucial for understanding AD pathogenesis as small-sized oligomer believed to be a key cause of neural loss in AD patients. We have used the game theory model to abstract the mass-action based non-linear, coupled dynamical system of competing pathways of aggregation. Through analysis, we found higher LD concentration leads to the generation of more micelle-bound oligomers (promoting the off-pathway of aggregation), higher levels of dilution of the medium result in dissociating micelle bound oligomers enabling higher conversion to fibrils (promoting the traditional on-pathway of aggregation). These models were subsequently validated by our previously developed ensemble kinetics simulations (EKS) that use ordinary differential equations based models of the competing pathways to estimate the rate constants of converting oligomers between on- and off-pathway aggregates&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular_communication</title>
      <link>/project/molecular_communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 21:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/molecular_communication/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Synthetic biologists endeavor to predict the increasing complexity of multistep signaling cascades impacts the fidelity of molecular signaling, whereby information about the cellular state is often transmitted with proteins that diffuse by a pseudo-one-dimensional stochastic process. This process raises the question of how the cell leverages passive transport mechanisms to distinguish informative signals from the intrinsic noise of diffusion. We addressed this problem by using a one-dimensional drift-diffusion model to derive an approximate lower bound on the degree of facilitation needed to achieve single-bit informational efficiency in signaling cascades as a function of their length. Within the assumptions of our model, we found that a universal curve of the Shannon-Hartley form describes the information transmitted by a signaling chain of arbitrary length and depends upon only a small number of physically measurable parameters. This methodology enables our model to be used in conjunction with experimental measurements to aid in the selective design of biomolecular systems that can overcome noise to function reliably, even at the single-cell level.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Supramolecular Structure from the Statistics of Individual Molecular Events</title>
      <link>/publication/pilkiewicz-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pilkiewicz-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Assembly from a Single-Molecule Perspective</title>
      <link>/publication/pilkiewicz-2019-assembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pilkiewicz-2019-assembly/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A game theoretic approach to deciphering the dynamics of amyloid- Ab aggregation along competing pathways</title>
      <link>/publication/ghosh-2019-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/ghosh-2019-game/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of the Common Molecular Basis in Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s Diseases</title>
      <link>/publication/rana-2019-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rana-2019-evaluation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Communication and Cellular Signaling from an Information-Theory Perspective</title>
      <link>/publication/pilkiewicz-2019-molecular/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/pilkiewicz-2019-molecular/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent advances on constraint-based models by integrating machine learning</title>
      <link>/publication/rana-2019-recent/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rana-2019-recent/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Smart Healthcare Portal for Clinical Decision Making and Precision Medicine</title>
      <link>/publication/nalluri-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/nalluri-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking the communication fidelity of biomolecular signaling cascades featuring pseudo-one-dimensional transport</title>
      <link>/publication/rana-2018-benchmarking/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rana-2018-benchmarking/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cause and consequence of Aβ – Lipid interactions in Alzheimer disease pathogenesis</title>
      <link>/publication/rangachari-2018-cause/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rangachari-2018-cause/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of an Aβ Dodecamer Strain Involves a Three-Step Mechanism and a Key Intermediate</title>
      <link>/publication/dean-2018-propagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/dean-2018-propagation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determining causal miRNAs and their signaling cascade in diseases using an influence diffusion model</title>
      <link>/publication/nalluri-2017-determining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/nalluri-2017-determining/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced and selective acetone sensing properties of SnO2-MWCNT nanocomposites: Promising materials for diabetes sensor</title>
      <link>/publication/narjinary-2017-enhanced/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/narjinary-2017-enhanced/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fatty Acid Concentration and Phase Transitions Modulate Aβ Aggregation Pathways</title>
      <link>/publication/rana-2017-fatty/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rana-2017-fatty/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strain-specific fibril propagation by an Aβ dodecamer</title>
      <link>/publication/dean-2017-strain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/dean-2017-strain/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capacity estimates of additive inverse Gaussian molecular channels with relay characteristics</title>
      <link>/publication/rana-2016-additive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/rana-2016-additive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Ti doping on the structural, electrical and magnetic properties of GaFeO3</title>
      <link>/publication/sen-2016-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/sen-2016-effect/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determining influential miRNA targets in diseases using influence diffusion model</title>
      <link>/publication/nalluri-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/nalluri-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nanocrystalline gallium ferrite: A novel material for sensing very low concentration of alcohol vapour</title>
      <link>/publication/sen-2015-nanocrystalline/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/sen-2015-nanocrystalline/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sonochemically prepared nanosized BiFeO3 as novel SO2 sensor</title>
      <link>/publication/das-2015-sonochemically/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/das-2015-sonochemically/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis, characterization and vapour sensing properties of nanosized ZnFe2O4</title>
      <link>/publication/maharajan-2014-synthesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/maharajan-2014-synthesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
